[MUSIC]
In our previous video, we compared spot
and forward prices on a relative basis.
Now in this video,
we'll explore two potential patterns,
contango and backwardation.
The usual spread between prices tells
us that forward prices are higher than
current prices.
This situation referred to as contango
is quite typical due to a variety
of factors such as inflation, insurance,
storage, and investor psychology.
However afford prices may also fall
below the current market price,
either on a short term basis or
for a sustained period.
When this happens, investors refer to
backwardation, which might occur when
there's been or there's expected to be
a shortage of the product in the near term
yet production is why they expected to
resume in the coming weeks and months.
Backwardation gets right to the very
heart of imminent supply and demand.
Now at this point you may be wondering why
your next door neighbor invests in corner
crude oil, and yet you haven't seen
their backyard crammed with stocks of
corner flooded in petroleum.
This is primarily because investors in the
futures market are able to transact and
take positions in and yet
never actually own, the commodity or
product they invest in.
At the same time, the liquid nature of
most futures markets makes it a viable
environment for producers to offset risk
and ultimately transact physical delivery.
In our next video, we'll take a closer
look at futures contracts and
provide you with an example of
a standardized crude oil contract.
We'll look forward to you joining us then.
[MUSIC]